So today we're going to make a no added
sugar salted caramel ice cream. This one
is incredible
ninja creamy. Super super easy to do as
well. So let's get on and make it.
As the thumbnail might have indicated,
I'm going to use alulose for this salted
caramel ice cream. Uh a quick thing
about caramelizing sugars. The sucrose
will caramelize. That's like the
benchmark for caramelization. doesn't
really change the chemical structure of
the sugar. I mean, it does a little bit.
It changes a little bit of that sucrose
into a little bit of glucose, a little
bit into slightly more fructose, but
ultimately it doesn't really change your
recipe that much. Doesn't change the
pack or the pod that much. Um, the only
time it changes your perceived sweetness
is when you burn it. When you when you
really caramelize it down to deep deep
dark brown color, then you increase the
bitter tones within that sugar and then
your perceived sweetness goes out the
window. So you need to kind of just keep
that in check. Alo as it's labeled as
like a unique sugar. It caramelizes much
easier than sucrose. So we need to be
careful with that. You cannot caramelize
xylitol if you're going to ask. It just
won't work. Just doesn't work. So, with
that said, what are we going to need for
this luxury ninja creamy salted caramel
ice cream? You are going to need 632 g
of light cream, which is 18% fat. In the
UK, that's single cream. We're going to
use 80 g of alos, 32 g of skim milk
powder, 3 g of salt, and 2 g of stevia
drops. Now, we need the stevia drops
because we're using alulos. We are
caramelizing our elos and it doesn't
produce the perceived sweetness required
for this ice cream. The stevia drops all
it does is increase the perceived
sweetness level. That that's it. It
makes it taste nice. Makes it taste nice
and sweet like ice cream kind of should
be, but not too sweet. We don't want it
incredibly sweet. We want it, you know,
somewhere in between. If you really hate
sweet ice cream, don't put it in. It has
no effect on your recipe other than
changing how you perceive the sweetness
level. With that said, let's get
everything weighed out. First thing
we're going to do is weigh our alulos,
and that is 80 g. We're going to weigh
this into a small pan because we're
going to caramelize this on its own. So,
this is powdered alulose. We need to be
careful with this. If you're using
granulated alos, you also have to be
careful, but it it's a bit more even
with caramelization. So, we're going to
get this on heat, mediumigh heat, and
we're going to keep this going until we
get the color that we want. Be careful
with the color. Trying to I'll put a
swatch up on the screen as to the the
level of brownness that we need. All
right, so let's get that going. And with
that doing its thing, we are going in
with our 18%
cream. So, single cream in the UK. I
don't know what you call it in the US.
I'm sure you have it, but um let me know
in the comments what your 18% cream is
called. Might just be called a light
cream. This is
just called cream. 632
g. And into our light cream, we are
going to put our skim milk powder, which
is 32 g. We're going to save our stevia
drops until the very end once the mix is
all done. So, let's get this all whisked
together.
And we're going to pop that on heat and
bring this up to a medium high
temperature. So, somewhere around a 60
70° C mark because we're adding that
boiling hot alulose into this. It needs
to be high temperature. So, let's get
that going. So, the only two things we
got left are our stevia and our salt.
Again, both of those going in at the
end. Let's get these two things going.
Once you start heating up your alos,
you'll see that it will start to turn,
you know, translucent around the edges.
Just keep swirling it manually and then
eventually it will bubble up like crazy
and over the course of about 10 seconds
the bubbles will disappear. This is
where you need to keep an eye on it.
Once we get to this kind of stage, we
need to really be careful that we don't
burn it. As you can see that alolo once
it starts to go, it goes incredibly
fast. It caramelizes much faster than
normal sugar. But we're at the color
that we want now. We've got our milk
heated up. We're going to pop some of
this into here. Watch the bubbling.
Nice. And while that's still warm, we're
going to put that straight into our
other pan.
You want to get as much of that out as
you can. You don't want to leave any in
there cuz that will affect your recipe.
So, make sure that all comes out. Now,
we can just stir this together. If your
milk isn't hot enough, you can just pop
it back on heat to redesolve those
sugars. You'll tell because it'll be on
the whisk. So, let's just give this a
stir for a minute. Make sure all those
sugar crystals, those alulose crystals
are completely dissolved into our dairy.
All right, we're completely whisked
together. The kitchen stinks cuz I got
some milk on the hob and it's burning
away. So, now we have our salt. We have
3 g of salt in this.
Don't add too much salt. Salt really
affects freezing point of your ice
cream. So if you add too much if you if
you like it really salty, you're going
to need to remove some alulos to to
rebalance that freezing point. Too much
salt won't freeze. And then finally, our
stevia.
And this is 2 g.
So that's about that. Stir that in.
There it is. Our delicious salted
caramel ice cream. Let's get that poured
into our container.
Loads of bubbles on the top. That is
just because we've been agitating the
cream. As you can see, the bubbles are
actually here. So, I'm going to keep
going. I'm going to remove those
bubbles.
They will settle down on their own.
But we can see that our level is here.
There's a certain amount of liquid left
in here. So, if we leave this just for a
little bit, this liquid level will rise
and our bubble level will drop and we
can scoop the rest off. There we go.
Completely full up to the line. You get
those bubbles for a couple of reasons.
A, it's a type of dairy feather blowing
around. Um, you agitate it, it increases
the air. You can't whip 18% fat cream
just won't it won't happen. But it will
incorporate air into it [clears throat]
to a degree. And that is what we are
left with here. Adding that hot liquid,
creating those intense bubbles that is
adding more air to it. So once we mix
them together, we've got this larger
amount of unrequired air bubbles in our
mix. We need those to reduce so we can
see exactly how much in our container we
have. If you leave them, they will
actually freeze. You'll get this weird
layer on the top and it will freeze and
your Ninja Creamy will be seriously
overfilled. But that top layer will be
really unpleasant to eat. So it's just
easier just to let it settle for a
couple of minutes, then take those off.
And now we can pop this in the freezer
and wait for it to harden off. Again,
it's going to take overnight. So, so
let's get that in and come back in the
morning and spin it.
Going to spin this on ice cream even
though it's gelato because the ice cream
and gelato settings do exactly the same
thing on this machine.
Right, let's get this one scooped up and
see how it turned out.
Right, time to try this.
Wow, beautiful taste. You've got to
watch the alos. If you take it too far,
you become quite bitter. So, you're
never going to get a super strong
caramel flavor because the bitter tones
come through much earlier when
caramelizing alos than they do if you're
caramelizing sucros. [music]
So, normal sugar. Thanks very much for
watching. Don't forget to like and
subscribe. And next week, I'm making a
very special ice cream for one of my
Patreon supporters who is diabetic.